can you imagine how our
ты представляешь насколько наша Вот
Russian culture is? Yes, it is poorer than the Ukrainian one,
русская культура Да беднее украинской
even if we look at the musical
если мы даже смотрим по музыкальному
instrument, we have a balalaika with three
инструменту у нас заст балалайка с тремя
strings, Yes, and the Ukrainians have a gusli
струнами при Да а у украинцев гусли есть
there, in short, a bandura, how much people had to
там короче бандура как насколько люди
be educated? Yes, in order to
должны были быть образованными Да чтобы
play the bandura, you understand how cattle you are
играть на бандуре ты понимаешь ско ты
played some kind of musical
играл на каком-то музыкальном
instrument no by the way
инструменте нет кстати
never Hello I am Samm But I live in
никогда Здравствуйте я самм Но живу в
California 18 years in 2 years it will be where
Калифорнии 18 лет через 2 года будет дто
you are
Вы
from From
откуда Из
Moscow I live in Moscow I understand you are not afraid to
Москвы живу в Москве понял не боитесь
hang such a flag in
такой флаг вывешивать в
Moscow no
Москве нет
no Well, especially in the apartment I think
нет Ну тем более в квартире я думаю
how old are you
сколько вам
19 years old brave
19 смел
Well, there’s nothing special about this,
Ну в этом ещё ничего
there are flags for which it’s kind of
такого есть флаги за которые как бы
possible that something here is kind of
можно чтото тут как бы
still possible And
ещё можно А
how do I communicate mainly in culture? What
чем общаюсь в основном культуре Что
exactly is culture? I’m just a teacher of
именно культуры Я просто преподаватель
cultural studies at the University of Sacramento, a
культурологии в университете Сакраменто
student of cultural studies, a
студент культурологии
geek and the Moscow Institute of Culture, I’m
гик и институт культуры московс
interested in what you can name.  you know the
интересно можешь назвать Какие ты знаешь
cultures in North
культуры в Северной
America Well, I must immediately warn you that
Америке Ну сразу должен предупредить что
I didn’t go through this topic of some kind.
я мы эту тему не проходили какого-то Ну
Well, look, wait, if you went
это же Смотри ты подожди если ты пошёл
to study cultural studies. It’s clear that you weren’t a
на культуролога Это ясно что ты не был
doctor until yesterday, yes, that is, you have
врачом до вчера да то есть у тебя есть
a background that means you  something
бэкграунд который то есть тебя что-то
led to this you were interested in this That
привело к этому ты интересовался этим То
is, you don’t just get into this specialty
есть на эту специальность просто так не
Yes, yes, of course I mean, among the
попадают Да да конечно В смысле среди
Indians, not only among the Indians,
индейцев не только среди индейцев
North America in Siena, not only Yaski
Северная Америка на сиена не только яски
Mos, there were a lot of Alites there But
Мос же были там алиты очень много А ну
well, the Alites are very interesting  I
да вот алиты очень интересно Мне
liked it Recently I was in the kun chamber
понравилось Недавно я был в кун камере
there was a very good exposition on
там была экспозиция очень хорошая по
Alium Alita the second tribe was Russian
алиум алиты второе племя вот русской
Alaska but
Аляски токо
Russian was
русской было
the name I don’t remember the second tribe
название не вспомню второе племя
was with which we would be based on
было с которым вот это мы по бы
the interactions of Russians
взаимодействиям русских
with I’m not sure I’m not sure I won’t
с не уверен не уверен не буду точно
say for sure there is in  kind of
говорить имеется в виду
cultures
культуры
indigenous I asked you how are the cultures of
коренные Я спросил тебя как вот культуры
North America
Северной Америки
well the cries of the Iroquois Comanches are you
хорошо крики ирокезы команчи это ты
the tribes you
племена
call the tribes yes yes well too yes well
называешь племена да да ну ли тоже да ну
I didn’t ask the tribes for example
я же не спросил племена например
culture what cultures are there in Europe You
культура какие культуры там Европы Ты
know Yes and you start talking there
знаешь Да и ты начинаешь говорить там
For example the
Например
Goths for example there  Frisians And so on,
готы например там фризы И так дальше это
you call them affiliations, tribes, and
ты называе принадлежности племена а
cultures, you are a culturologist,
культуры ты культуролог
or Well, first year. So okay, good. Eh,
или Ну первый курс Так ладно хорошо Ээ
let’s do this. Give me a definition of
давай так Дай мне определение
culture, culture - it’s all created
культуры культура - это всё создано
by man. Well, this is one of the definitions of
человеком А ну это одно из определений
culture. I think it’s pretty limited;
культуры Мне кажется оно довольно уреза
everything was created by man.
всё создано человеком
Then I’ll
Тода
improvise  Come on, come on, let's throw a log
импровизирую Дава давай давай так мостик
across the river, it's
через речку вот перекинули бревно это
culture, well, you see, it was created by
культура м ну да видишь создано
man, but it's not culture, it's
человеком но это не культура
really materially
правда материально
intangible
нематериальное
Heritage yes Well, look why For
Наследие да Ну вот смотри почему
example, a bridge
Например мостик
Yes, it won't be an element of material
Да не будет элементом материальной
culture, it's a material object, but it's
культуры он материальный объект но это
not an object of material culture Yes, for
не объект материальной культуры Да
example  a
например
painted pot is an element of
расписанный горшок есть элементом
material culture, and a stick that is
материальной культуры а палка которая
thrown across a century in order to
там кинута через веку чтобы по ней
cross it Yes, this is not an element of
перейти Да это не есть элемент
material culture What is culture?
материальной культуры Что такое культура
Well, at the same time, a bridge, for example, of some kind from the 10th
Ну при этом мост например какой-нибудь X
century is an element of culture,
века является элементом культуры
no, a bridge is an engineering
нет мост - это есть инженерное
structure, elements of a bridge Yes  can be
сооружение элементы моста Да могут быть
elements of material
элементами материальной
culture. Well, for example,
культуры Ну например
some San Francisco
вот сан-франциско
bridge, this is culture, too, this is
мост это же культура тоже это
architecture, this is engineering skill,
архитектура это инженерное мастерство
look again, the elements of the bridge can be
ещё раз смотри элементы моста могут быть
elements of material culture, the
элементами материальной культуры сам
bridge itself - it was just
мост - это просто
made, and the bridge was made for a reason in order
его сделали да мост сделали для чего для
to demonstrate  your inner
того чтобы проявить свою внутреннюю там
essence there is folk yes Or just a bridge
суть народную да Или просто мост для
to move from one place to
того чтобы перейти с одного места в
another you understand For example,
другое понимаешь Вот например
I’ll explain it to you like this when a woman Yes takes
объясню тебе так когда женщина Да берёт
and for example
и например
paints an egg for Easter
раскрашивает яйцо на Пасху
Yes, she does this for
Да вот она это делает для
what purpose in order to eat
чего для того чтобы съесть
partly in order to eat  and partly
отчасти для того чтобы съесть и отчасти
to
чтобы
show your inner creativity, yes, that
проявить сво внутренее творчество да то
is, culture is, first of all, a
есть культура - это в первую очередь
projection into the real world of a person’s inner world,
проекция в реальный мир внутреннего мира
that is, when a song Yes, we
человека то есть когда песня Да мы
make a song, oral folk art
делаем песню устное народное творчество
is an element of intangible
это элемент нематериальной
culture You are already a first-year student, in
культуры Вы же это ули уже первый курс
any case, really
по-любому правда
what  some
какие-нибудь
ideas
идей может
maybe literature is probably literature in principle
быть литература наверное в принципе
Yes, then what
литература Да дальше что
else is cinema cinema right
ещё кинематограф кинематограф правильно
what
что
else is this in my opinion
ещ это помоему
lectures these are the first lectures like you music
лекции это первые лекции как ты музыка
Yes poems And so on Well why do you take so long to
Да поэмы И так дальше Ну что так долго
remember
вспоминаешь
jokes mythology Yes sayings jokes yes
анекдоты мифология Да поговорки шутки да
these are all elements of intangible culture
это всё элементы нематериальной культуры
Well  listen This is what you should, as a
Ну слушай Это ты должен как студент
cultural studies student, call a gathering
культуролог это называть сход у тебя
at night, they should wake you up, name examples of
ночью должны разбудить назвить примеры
intangible culture in me If a
нематериальной культуре у меня Если бы
student on an exam, I asked him
студент на экзамене я его спросил да
what elements and he would start thinking I would
какие элементы и он начал бы думать Я бы
send him for a retake
отправил на пересдачу
yes yes students are capable are
да да студенты есть способны есть
incapable interested  Yes Not
неспособные заинтересованные есть Не
interested Well, do you consider yourself
заинтересованные ну ты себя считаешь
capable
способным
Interested I don’t know I don’t know well
заинтересованным не знаю не знаю хорошо
that’s also an interesting question from the elements of the
вот интересный тоже вопрос из элементов
material
материальной
culture of the Russian ethnic group Yes, can you
культуры русского этноса Да можешь мне
name me the Russian national
назвать русскую национальную
shoes of the material culture of the Russian
обувь материальной культуры русского
ethnic group Yes, you can call Russian shoes bast shoes, bast shoes
этноса Да обувь русскую мо можеш назвать
Look, Why when we
лапти лапти Вот смотри Почему когда мы
say for example  uh, some Turkic
говорим например ээ у каких-то тюркских
peoples Yes, there will be different leather
народов Да будут разные там кожаная
shoes and felt boots there, all sorts of felt ones
обувь да валенки там всякие войлочные
Ukraine Lithuania Poland also have leather ones And
Украина Литва Польша тоже там кожаные И
so on and Russian bast shoes Why so, well,
так дальше а русские лапти Почему
by the way, It seems to me that
Я кстати Мне кажется у
many, say, ethnic groups besides the Russians
многих скажем этносов помимо русских Вот
have similar ones in this latitude
в этой широте условно встречаются
that is, it’s not always the same, it’s not
похожие то есть не всегда же это же не
always the leather that will be there if you take it at the ball.
всегда кожа будет если взять при бал
Look, not the Baltic countries leather, the
Смотри не е страны балтии кожа страны
Baltic countries leather, that is, in the European
балтии кожа то есть они в Европейском
context they were completely Yes, leather
контексте были полностью Да кожаная
shoes like or there were floors in bast shoes, they didn’t
обувь типа или там пол в лаптях не
wear bast shoes in the Baltics at all, no, well, that’s it  not
ходили в балтии вообще нет ну это же не
always leather shoes have been there since eleven
всегда кожаная обувь там с одиннад д
centuries for all groups of the population, there
веков для всех групп населения там же
probably would have been eyelids and leather, look, there were
навер бы веко и кожа смотри были
special leathers Yes,
специальные кожемяки Да
those who processed the leather were not with us,
которые обрабатывали кожу не у нас же
too, they were in Russia, this was the
тоже были в России это Это был ка то
character that walked, it was Ivan,
ходил персонаж был Иван
not this, Kirill's leather, this  among the Ukrainians
не это Кирилла кожемяка это у украинцев
this is among the Ukrainians a character he beat a dragon like
это у украинцев персонаж он дракона типа
Yes Kirill
побил Да Кирилла
Kozhemyak He Yes here among the Ukrainians
кожемяка Он Да вот у украинцев потому
because uh Ukraine Yes as the Heir of Kievan
что ээ Украина Да как Наследник Киевской
Rus they had yes leather
Руси у них было да кожаные изделия
workshops they went like the Ukrainians
мастерские они ходили типа вот украинцы
don’t know such
лапти не знают такого
bast shoes True Well, of course I
Правда Ну я конечно
still
всё-таки
no no not a professor of cultural studies, I
не не не профессор культурологии я не
can’t say for sure, but it seems to me that I
могу точно сказать но мне кажется у меня
still have the feeling that
всё равно есть такое ощущение что
leather shoes, even say, in countries
кожаная обувь даже скажем в странах как
like Poland, Lithuania, this region,
бы Польши Литвы Вот вот этого региона
I think it was still not for all
Мне кажется всё-таки не для всех
classes,
сословий
I have this feeling  if you
было у меня есть такое ощущение если
take Germany, it seems to me yes, but
взять Германию Мне кажется да но вот
there further to the
туда дальше на
east I’m just kind of
восток Я просто как бы
different from what, for example, in
чем чем от чем отличалось например в
Germany and in Poland, like the class
Германии и в Польше типа сословие также
was also like the class, it was just technology already. The
типа сословно было просто технологии уже
fact is that you understand that
Дело в том что ты понимаешь что
processing technologies already existed, how
технологии обработки уже были как
these were done  bast shoes, yes, you, uh, didn’t really have
делались эти лапти да ты ээ не было
a life, yes, because if we
животи толком да Потому что если мы
look at the territory there is the same
смотрим территория там же той же
modern Ukraine Poland Lithuania Yes, people
современной Украины Польши Литвы Да люди
were engaged in agriculture and had a
занимались и сельским хозяйством и имели
lot of livestock And so on, yes,
очень много голов скота И так дальше да
that is, they had the material to
то есть у них был материал для того
process it  Yes, because
чтобы это обрабатывать Да потому что
now we have the
сейчас у нас тут
Sacramento Tornado here. And yes, when a
Торнадо Сакраменто А да у нас когда
Tornado approaches, we sound the
Торнадо подходит у нас включают
air
воздушную
raid alarm. Because if you don’t hide with
тревогу Потому что если не спрячешься у
us, I don’t live close to the ocean.
нас Я то живу не близко возле океана Вот
But whoever lives near the ocean must
Но кто живёт возле океана то надо быстро
evacuate quickly because I saw it.  there
эвакуироваться потому что вот видел Вот
was a hurricane in Florida the other
этот по Флориде прол ураган на
day, so it’s tough there,
днях там жесть
so I have a house like this, it turns out that my house has a
поэтому у меня такой у меня дом
basement, I’ll
получается с подвальный помещением я так
say this, that is, I’m protected, but who
скажу то есть у меня защищено а кто Вот
in these small houses, you
в этих таких небольших домиках да то
need to run away, I understand So look, and
нужно убегать понял Так вот смотри и
bast shoes turn out to be bast shoes like you  I went and
лапти получается лапти как ты пошёл
tore the bast from the birch bark from the birch and weaved
надрал лыка с бересты с берёзы и плетёшь
paws, that is, I collected some
лапки то есть насобирал какого-то
material. This is from birch and everything is like
материала Вот это из берёзы и всё вот
that. For example, you can name
так также например вот можешь назвать
the elements
элементы
from the Russian ethnic group, what kind of
из у русского этноса какие
culinary
есть кулинарные
products they have. Well, mostly grain products. I
изделия Ну в основном хлебные Мне
think they will be
кажется это будут
from all sorts of cultures.  such millet
из культур всяких таких пшено
rye Well, what is the name, name the name,
рож Ну как название вот назви название
for example, some soups, porridge, etc. What kind of
например какие-то супы каши там ещ Какие
dishes do the Russians have?
блюда у русских
Well, I don’t know, to be honest, when dumplings
Ну я не знаю если честно когда пельмени
are folded, dumplings are not dumplings, definitely
складываются пельмени не пельмени точно
not Russian dumplings
не Русские пельмени -
are Finno-Ugric dumplings, they are
это фино угорские пельмени - это
Mari there, Mordovian, yes, it’s not
марийские там мордовски да это не
Russians
русские
for sure Well, they’re still the same
точно Ну они же всё равно это же
interaction, don’t look at this, it’s
взаимодействие не смотри это
definitely borrowed from the EU dumplings, we pori
заимствовано точно пельмени ЕС мы пори
dumplings have spread
пельмени распространились в
among the Parsi Yes, among the Russians this is the 20th century
среди парси Да среди русских это 20 век
Yes, if we look at them, they
Да если мы посмотрим дево никаких
didn’t make any dumplings in Russian villages
пельменей в русских деревнях не
Well, they appear there in Korea
делали Ну они же появляются там в Корее
in  Georgia There are the same meni conventional food
в Грузии Там те же мени условные ёд вки
No, look at this in Georgia it
Нет смотрите в этом в Грузии это Хинкали
would be Khinkali su as an analogue of essentially dumplings
бы су как аналог по сути пельменей
only in a different way Yes but
только по-другому ещё Да но
uh Show me the same Show me look,
э Покажи мне су же Покажи мне вот смотри
take for example at least one uh there is a
возьми например хоть один ээ там
work by Pushkin yes Or else  someone
произведение Пушкина да Или ещё кого-то
from the classico and find dumplings there
из классико и найди там пельмени
you won’t find any mentions No, well there Of course
упоминаний не найдёшь Не ну там Конечно
I don’t think it will be there That’s because
я не думаю что там будет Вот потому что
look They kind of described
смотри Они что как как бы они описывали
what happened
то что было
then The Tale of the Priest and his workers
тогда вот Сказка о попе и его работники
Balda remember Pushkin taught at school  I
Балде помнишь Пушкина учил в школе
don’t know what kind of culturologist this is,
не знаю пра что это за культуролог
fir-trees. And there it was that they ate
ёлки-палки Вот И там было что что Ели
spelled, spelted, you ate, you know what
полбу полбу ели знаеш что такое
spelled is, this type of cereal like wheat
полба такой вид злаковых типа пшеницы
was common, they ate it, steamed it, and they
был распространён Вот её ели запарили и
ate turnips, no dumplings, but if you
ели никаких пельменей вот если ты
look at
посмотришь
my memories
воспоминаний ме
in any-  then years nowhere, that is, dumplings
ни в каких-то лет нигде то есть пельмени
- these are borrowed from certain
- это заимствованный у определённых там
Finno-Ugric peoples in the 10th century, in fact, they
фино угорских народов в X веке по сути
became
стали
popular Well, yes, yes, I think yes And music,
популярны Ну да да я думаю да А музыка
musical instruments Yes, here are Russian
музыкальные инструменты Да вот русские
musical instruments What does it mean
музыкальные инструменты Какие значит
if there are elements of material
если там элементы материальной
culture, so gusli seems to be a Ukrainian
культуры так гусли кажется украинский
instrument gusli  Yes Ukrainian Yes you are
инструмент гусли Да украинский Да это ты
right
прав
m Balalaika balalaika Turkic even
м Балалайка балалайка тюркская даже
the word balalai
слово балалай
is Turkic is Turkic here komuz yes it is
тюркское есть тюркский вот комуз да это
round with three strings And so on the
круглая с тремя струнами И так дальше
Thai komuz but eh balalaika is
таец комуз но э балалайка - это есть
a type of komuz just that’s all And
разновидность комуза просто вот и всё И
if we look at the Turkic
если если мы посмотрим да у тюркских
ethnic groups  on the komuz there are a lot of
этносов на комузе очень много есть
different ones, or everything on the balalaika,
разных там ило всё на балалайке
that’s what just
вот что просто её
popularized it, make some kind of picture
популяризировал какую-то картинку
there like a dude, a Bear and a
сделать там типа чувак Медведь и
balalaika, that’s all And
балалайка вот и всё А
so, well, it seems to me that they are
так ну мне же кажется
borrowing all these
там заимствование вот этих всех
instruments, if you look at the
инструментов всего если посмотри вот у
Ukrainians Yes, the bandura  Have you seen How many
украинцев Да бандура ты видел Сколько
strings a bandura has And how many strings a balalaika has,
струн у бандуры И сколько у балалайки
even the
даже
truth of the bandura is like this Yes, it’s
правда бандуры такая вот она Да такая
like a big drop and there are a lot of
как бы как капля большая да и там куча
strings Yes, just 50-something or even
струн Да просто 50 с чем-то или даже
more Can you imagine how this one
больше представляешь как этот вот
[music]
[музыка]
he just mentioned
э который называл только что
kamus no no not not me who at first Yes, the
камус не не не не я который сначала Да
psaltery is like the psaltery, only the psaltery is a little Yes,
гусли как гусли только гусли немножко Да
look, the psaltery was placed vertically
смотри гусли они ставились вертикально
Yes, uh Well, the psaltery has even fewer strings and
Да вот ээ Ну у гусли ещё меньше струн да
than the bandura, the bandura has a lot of strings, yes,
чем у бандуры у бандуры вообще много да
that is, you can imagine how ours is
то есть представляешь насколько наша Вот
Russian culture Yes, poorer than Ukrainian
русская культура Да беднее украинской
even if we look at the musical
если мы даже смотрим по музыкальному
instrument, we borrowed a balalaika
инструменту у нас заимствована балалайка
and three strings, brin brin brin Yes, and the
и тремя струнами бринь бринь бринь Да а
Ukrainians have a gusli there, in short, a
у украинцев гусли есть там короче
bandura, how educated did people have to
бандура как насколько люди должны были
be? Yes, to play the
быть образованными Да чтобы играть на
bandura, you understand how long you have played
бандуре ты понимаешь ну сколько ты играл
on some musical instrument  no,
на каком-то музыкальном инструменте нет
by the way,
кстати
I never played the guitar Yes, six strings
никогда Я на гитаре играл Да Шесть струн
Yes, and I understand that those people who
Да и я понимаю что те люди которые на
learned to play this bandura, yes, without
этой бандуре учились играть да это без
these simulators And so on, that is,
этих тренажёров И так дальше то есть
how developed it was. You
насколько было развито Вот это
understand this cultural heritage Well, yes, so it
культурное наследие понимаешь Ну да Так
seems to me that this still had an influence  Proximity
что мне кажется это ещё влияло Близость
to Europe, after all, and being there,
к Европе всё-таки и вот нахождение в том
including as part of the
числе в составе там
Lithuanian Yes, the civilized world Yes, the
литовского Да цивилизованный мир Да
civilized world, to exchange
цивилизованный мир обмениваться
some of
какими-то
these uh achievements Absolutely true Yes,
этими ээ достижениями Абсолютно верно Да
people thought differently, people
люди по-другому мыслили люди образованы
were educated, yes something like that yes And you yourself
были да какой-то вот так да А ты сам
where do your ancestors come from from black
родом откуда твои предки из чернозём
soil black soil more specifically Tambov Lipetsk understood
чернозем конкретнее Тамбов Липецк понял
Yes, Tambov Gubernia, historically
Да ну Тамбовская Губерния исторически
speaking, there
сказать там же
were principalities there that were
были княжество которое в большее
borrowed to a greater extent to a lesser extent, for example, the Principality of Novgorod, which to a
заимствовали в меньшей степени например
greater
Новгородское княжество оно же в большей
extent, the Principality of Novgorod
степени Новгородское княжество вообще не
has nothing to do with Russians at all. The
имеет к русским никакого отношения Дело
fact is that Novgorod  the principality became
в том что Новгородское княжество вошло в
part of the Moscow state Yes, after
состав московского государства Да после
the capture there in the 10th or 10th century Yes, when
захвата там в X или в X веке Да когда
Moscow captured the Novgorodians, they
Московская захватила новгородцев
exterminated all the Novgorodians and simply
истребили всех новгородцев да и просто
seized the territory, it’s all in the
захватили территорию это же есть всё в
chronicles, that is, the Novgorod
летописях то есть Новгородское
principality there
княжество там
are the Ilmen tribes of the Slovenes Yes, they
это племена ильменские словене Да они к
lived in Moscow  there, the Moscow
москви которые жили там Московской
modern region of the Yaroslavl Tasha
современной области Ярославской таши не
had nothing to do with it, that is,
имели никакого отношения то есть
the territory of Novgorod is the same as
территория Новгорода это также как
the territory of Kiev, and for example, then the
территория Киева да например потом
Russian Empire
Российская империя
captured these territories of Ukraine. Yes, the
захватила эти территории Украины Да
former Kievan Rus itself
бывшей Киевской Руси так само и
captured Novgorod, so
захватила Новгорода вот и
they were still in some kind of
всё всё равно находились в каком-то вот
communication like this  more or less, the language
таком общении более-менее язык же
was still there before, say, the division
всё-таки был там до скажем разделения
into these Belarusian Ukrainian ones.
на вот эти вот белорусские украинские
Back when Russia was like that,
Вот ещё когда Русь такая была
look and see when
относительно егда смотри да смотри когда
Russia was united. Yes, on the territory of the
Русь была единая Да на территории
Moscow region there was no Slavic language at all,
Московской области никакого вообще языка
that is, they lived there
Славянского не было да то есть там жили
not Slavic Fino-Ugric tribes, uh The
не славянские фино угорские племена ээ
fact is that modern Russians are a
Дело в том что современные русские - это
different conglomerate of Fino-Ugric
разный конгломерат народов фино угорских
Turkic peoples who simply adopted the
тюркских которые просто приняли
Slavic language of donkeys, so to
славянский язык ослов с можно так
speak. The fact is that from Kiev and
сказать Дело в том что из Киева да
missionaries came to these cities Yes,
миссионеры приезжали В эти города Да
which were founded and taught the local
которые основывались и учили местное
population to write  and read, since there
население писать и читать поскольку
were no letters in those territories, they
письма на тех территориях не было им
were brought Slavic initial letters Yes, and
приносили славянские буквицы Да и
accordingly they were taught in
соответственно на учили на
Church Slavonic, so it’s just
церковно-славянском поэтому это также
like
как вот э такую функцию использова
Latin used to perform such a function in Western Europe, and for
исполняла латынь в Западной Европе да
example, that is, there were Kel tribes there,
например вот то есть были там племена
and it turns out  Latin Zro
кель всё да и их получается латини Зро
Romaniva they had to read the church there
романива им приходилось там церковь
in Latin they wrote in Latin everyone
читала на латыни писали на латыне все
studied Latin here they studied
изучали латынь тут изучали
Church Slavonic And so on and in this
церковнославянский И так дальше и таким
way they already know Yes, she began to
образом знать уже Да она начинала
speak in these languages ​​​​about the Slavs, that’s all
говорить на вот этих таких о славяни
if we look Yes,
языках вот и всё если мы посмотрим Да
no Slavs Yes,
никаких славян Да
that’s 7  9th century in these territories there
вот 7 9 век на этих территориях не
was no Moscow Where did the
существовало где Московского Откуда Там
Moscow Principality come from? Yes And if we
Московское княжество пошло да И если мы
take the toponym Moscow is not a Slavic
возьмём топоним Москва не славянское
name Yes, damn the
название Да вот кля не
Slavs are not the princes, most of the majority of
славян принци большинство большинство
villages near Moscow
деревень рядом с Москвой
nors about
норс об
this, the thing is that until what
этом дело в том что до какого до
century? Yes,  there
даже века Да по сути мобильности
was no such thing as mobility of the population, and those people
населения такого не было да и те люди
who lived in these villages were
которые проживали в этих деревнях по
essentially ancestors. Heirs of those people
сути это предки Наследники тех людей
who lived here and there for 200 and 300 and 400
которые жили там и там 200 и 300 и 400
years, that’s all. And in Russia, yes, there
лет вот и всё А в России да правители
were rulers. All some Germans, that is.
были Все какие-то немцы так то есть
take everything if we take there Peter I
возьми все если мы возьмём там Пётр I
Catherine Elizabeth that’s all The Germans were
Катерины Елизавет это всё Немцы были
German dynasties
немецкие династии
and if we take for example Novgorod it’s
а если взять например Новгород аже
still
всё-таки
ethnically What is the population of Novgorod
этнически Какое население что Новгород
which was historically Yes the population
который был исторически Да население
was ethnic Ilmen Slovenes this is a
были этнические ильменские словене это
Slavic group Yes Novgorod
Славянская группа такая Да Новгородский
language  linguists distinguish it as
язык был его лингвисты выделяют Как ещё
another fourth language, like Belarusian
один четвёртый язык как вот белорусский
Ukrainian Russian modern Yes, from
украинский русский современные Да что из
Novgorod,
Новгородского да
another fourth
должен был сформироваться ещ четвёртый
East Slavic language should have been formed, but due to the fact
восточнославянский язык да но из-за того
that the Muscovites when they captured Novgorod
что московиты когда захватили Новгород
destroyed the entire population Yes, in fact,
уничтожили всё население Да по сути как
it was all
бы это всё
broken then  there is
оборвалось то есть
Novgorod Moscow and Russia
Новгород Москва и Россия к истории
have nothing to do with the history of Novgorod Yes, it’s
Новгорода вообще ничего не имеет Да это
essentially like, for example, the
по сути как например
Turks captured Constantinople Yes, they
турки захватили Константинополь Да
called it Istanbul There’s no longer there, the
назвали его Стамбул Там уже там нету всё
Turks live there now, that’s all, and
там турки живут теперь вот и всё так и
the Muscovites captured the city, slaughtered the
московиты захватили город вырезали
local population who fled, everything just
местное население кто бежал всё просто
remained  territory there, the resettlement
осталось территория там же переселение
was of the Novgorod elite to Moscow and
было Новгородской элиты в Москву а
the Moscow elite to Novgorod,
Московской в Новгород никакие
no Novgorod elites moved to Moscow,
Новгородские элиты в Москву не
they were all slaughtered, and the
переселялись их вырезали все а
Moscow elites settled, like
московские элиты да заселяли типа
the territory of Novgorod And like And all the other
территории Новгорода И как И всех других
occupied
захваченных
lands
земель
Yeah yeah
Угу да
What do you think Why Our Russia Yes is
Как ты считаешь Почему Наша Россия Да
so behind  of the entire
настолько отстаёт от всего
civilized
цивилизованного
world
мира
Well,
Ну
I’ll think about it for a couple of seconds, in
я пару секунд
general I had the feeling
подумаю вообще у меня было ощущение
that NUP was
что вот НУП
just, as it were, my own feeling that the
просто как бы своим ощущения что чем
farther from, as it were, Europe, the more
дальше от как бы Европы тем как бы чем
peripheral,
периферийные
that’s correct. Yes,
тем это правильно Да а
why
почему
geography, that geography, that
география что география что в Европе
there’s some kind of volcano in Europe  which distributes
какой-то там вулкан который раздаёт
some kind of energy or that Well, there is
какую-то энергию или что Ну есть
a feeling that Yes, it is a little
ощущение что Да немножко
possible because of the large
возможно из-за больших
territories, the more territories they are
территорий чем больше территорий чем они
not. The less competition, the
не Чем меньше конкуренция тем как бы
less, as it were. The incentive for
меньше Стимул к
development is possible,
развитию возможно так
so the Roman Empire
вот Римская империя огромнейшее
controlled a huge territory
территории контролировала
Yes, it has developed so far  buildings
Да развивалась какие до сих пор строения
by the state at that time Well, they were originally
государством те вре Ну они же изначально
tribes of these Latins,
вот племена как бы вот этих вот латин
they were squeezed between the cowards between the
они же были зажаты между труска между
Greeks. That is, yes Well, the same thing
греками То есть была же да Ну так так же
here, once upon a time, Moscow was a small
и тут когда-то там Москва была маленькое
tribe there, in short, and so on Yes Well  that's
племя там короче и так дальше Да Ну вот
how it turns out yes What
как так получается да Что
uh Despite all the enormous resources
ээ Несмотря на все огромнейший ресурсы
yes
да
And despite the fact that from the North there the
И несмотря на то что с Севера вот там
Arctic Ocean makes it
Северный Ледовитый океан даёт
possible for no one to attack from the
возможность чтобы никто не нападал с
North yes that is, you have huge
Севера да то есть ты имеешь огромные
territories a huge number of people
территории огромное количество людей
resources Yes and so all
ресурсов Да и так все
polymers Well  I would not say that this
полимеры Ну я бы не сказал что м такая
situation is very strong, there is some kind of
ситуация очень уж сильно какая-то есть
backwardness, there is some kind of
отсталость сильно есть какой-то вот
strong backwardness, strong, look, we are
сильная отсталость сильная смотри мы
losing now, when I was still living in
сейчас проигрываем вот я когда ещё жил в
Rostov, I thought that America will
Ростове Я думал а что там-то Америка
stand there now, we are all Sky and  earth, you know,
сейчас постою Всё мы Небо и земля знаешь
we are thinking about how to bomb
мы думаем как короче разбомбить там
some kind of Mariupol there, like yes, Kiev, and
какой-то Мариуполь типа да Киев а
America is thinking about how to launch a pancake into
Америка думает Как запустить блин в
space, in short, Damn, so that people
космос короче ещё Блин так чтобы людей
can be cheaply transported into space Ponya
можно было дёшево возить в космос Поня
Well, it’s simple that we now have
Ну просто Что у нас сейчас есть
computers - it’s all America and telephones
компьютеры - это всё Америка да телефоны
everything America Electronics America all
всё Америка Электроника Америка все
technologies America what we are What
технологии Америка что мы вот Что вот ты
can you say over the last 30 years that
можешь за последние 30 лет сказать что
Russia No, I absolutely agree on this
Россия Нет я абсолютно согласен в этом
issue yes Yes,
вопросе да Да
well, in terms of the fact
ну в плане того
that if we take Georgia for example, I
что если взять например Грузию я недавно
was recently in Georgia, in fact I was there three times.
в Грузии был вообще там три раза был вот
now 3 months ago I arrived, there is
сейчас 3 месяца назад приехал есть
a feeling that in Georgia the situation is even worse,
ощущение что в Грузии ситуация ещё хуже
as it were, economically and there because
как бы и экономически и там потому что
it’s clear because Russia attacked
это Понятно Потому что Россия напала на
Georgia Yes, Russia squeezed the territory from Georgia
Грузию Да у России отжала у Грузии
Russia squeezed the territory there in the form of a type of
России отжала территорию там в виде типа
not
не
Seva Osa there is this not Give the opportunity  It’s
Севе Осе есть это не Дат возможность
normal for Georgia to develop normally, it’s normal for
Грузии нормально развиваться нормально
investors to invest, that is, there is
инвестировать инвесторы не приходит то
uncertainty there because
есть там неопределённость потому что
maybe Russia again, that’s all, everything is
может Россия ещё раз вот и всё тут всё
simple with
просто с
Georgia, no. Well, they still left Georgia, as if they were part of
Грузией нет Ну они же ещё из состава как
Georgia. Georgia hasn’t
бы Грузии вышли Она же Грузия их не
controlled them since the collapse of the Soviet
контролировала с распада Советского
Union, these
Союза эти
territories are like that.  what do you think?
территории так че как ты считаешь
Well, at the moment it’s
Ну на данный момент он
Russian, as it were. What does Crimea mean at the
российский как бы по Что значит на
moment - what kind of
момент Крым - это какая
country? Well,
страна Ну
this is the territory that is
вот территория которая
essentially governed by the
управляется по
governor, it
сути губернатор
seems the president of the republic
кажется президент республи
is Aksyonov, it seems again, look if
это Аксёнов кажется ещё раз смотри если
I took your car, stole it and I’m driving  I
я взял у тебя машину украл и Катаюсь на
fill it with gasoline
ней заправляю её Да бензином Это чья
Yes, whose car is it? Well, yours, you dispose of it
машина Ну ваша вы распоряжаетесь ним ещё
again You didn’t steal it, but it’s yours until
раз Вы е украли но она Ваша на тот до
that moment, but if the police
того момента по то если полиция меня
stop me Yes, I say, I stole It’s
останавливает Да я говорю я украл Это
my car, okay That’s it, since it’s yours You
моя машина а окей Всё да раз твоя Ты же
stole everything
украл всё да
yes Well, they’ll ask whose car you’re
Ну вот они же спросит На чьей машине ты
driving in another but I’ll say It’s mine I
едешь на другой но я скажу Это на моей я
stole it in terms of ownership it won’t be
украл в плане собственности это будет не
your car whose Crimea is in terms of
Ваша машина то чей Крым в плане
ownership Crimea is what kind of
собственности Крым - это какая
country Well until 2014 it was Ukraine
страна Ну до 2014 года это была Украина
then that happened  the referendum is fair,
потом произошёл референдум честный
dishonest and then it’s lo Russian
нечестный и потом это ло россие страны
international countries didn’t
международные это не
recognize it That is, you support
признали То есть ты ты поддерживаешь
the seizure of Crimea No, I don’t support I’m
захват Крыма Нет я не поддерживаю Я
just saying, as if Ukraine thinks that
просто говорю как бы Украина считает что
Crimea is Ukrainian,
Крым украинский по ты как
but what do you think? Yes, I don’t think it’s like
считаешь Да я никак не считаю мне как бы
you’re doing something  I said for the referendum Well,
ты что-то за референдум сказывал Ну ты
what do you think Crimea is - what kind of
как считаешь Крым - это какая
country is it? No, well, I think that now Crimea
страна Нет ну я считаю что сейчас Крым
is governed by Russia, it invests,
управляется Россией инвестици вает
Russia does everything, Russia does it, Yes,
Россия всё делает Россия гово Да вот так
just like, for example, the one who stole the car. He is
же как например тот Кто украл машину Он
filling up the car now. Yes, he wipes it and takes it
заправляет сейчас машину Да протирает её
to the car wash. Yes, investments.  does yes
на мойку возит Да инвестиции делает да
it Stolen car then Crimea is what
это Украденная машина то Крым это какая
country do you
страна ты как
think from the point of view of international
считаешь с точки зрения международного
law is it part of Ukraine from your point of view
права это часть Украины с точки зрения
Well I don’t know Well I think So I
тебя Ну я не знаю Ну я считаю Вот я
think using the example of a car I think that
считаю на примере с машиной Я считаю что
if a person stole a car
если это человек украл машину
it’s very far away  and uses it all his life
е очень далеко и пользуется ею всю жизнь
Well, it can be
Ну она может быть
stolen from anywhere Anytime, but
украдена откуда угодно Когда угодно но
if he uses it all his life
если он ей будет пользоваться всю жизнь
he will say it’s my car. I understand, if
он скажет это моя машина Поня если
a person steals
человек украдёт
a child, it’s his
ребёнка это его
child. Yes, it’s like in Victor
ребёнок Да это вот как в романе Виктора
Hugo’s novel with Smeraldo. She’s a gypsy, but she’s
Гюго с смеральдо Она же цыганка но она
she is not a gypsy, but she is a gypsy,
она не цыганка но она цыганка
just in fact, at the moment the
просто по факту на данный момент город
city of Sudzha, Kursk region, is what kind of
город Суджа Курской области это какая
country is it now occupied by Ukraine?
страна сейчас она оккупирована Украиной
What does occupied mean? Well, that is, there
Что значит оккупирована Ну то есть там
are troops there and there is essentially a
находится войска и там по сути как
state of martial law there, and
бы состояние военного положения так а
Crimea is what kind of
Крым это какая
country Well, for  Crimea, there are simply no military operations
страна Ну за Крым просто боевые действия
being carried out, if there were, then no one is
не ведутся если бы велись то там так из
conducting military operations there because of the suju.
за суджу не ведутся боевые действия
Well, that is, I’m just
никто не ведёт Ну то есть я просто как
like, I’m not going to
бы я не буду как
argue, I’ll just explain how it
бы спорить просто объясню как как мне
seems to me how it works, well, look at it, it’s
кажется как это работае ну смотри за же
also not  There are military operations going on there, the
тоже не идут боевые действия всё там
Ukrainian army is standing up and everything is
украинская армия встала и всё всё там
all calm there, no, there are no trials
уже всё спокойно нет Там же там же
going on there, no, there are no trials going on, there are not being carried out
ведутся нет суд же не ведутся в суд же
in Crimea, there are arrivals in Crimea,
не ведутся А в Крыму ведутся в Крыму
yes, Ukraine is shelling
прилёты есть да Украина обстреливает
Crimea, the navy is knocking out the navy is
Крым военный флот выбивает как раз там
being carried out right there  military operations No, well, in the
ведутся боевые действия Не ну и в
Kursk region now they are
Курской области сейчас там они
there, how is the situation with Crimea different from the
там чем ситуация с Крымом отличается от
situation with the Kursk region there is
ситуации с Курской областью там
an occupation there, for example,
оккупация там вот есть например Польша
pre-war Poland there,
там до довоенная
wait don’t tell me Poland Look,
подожди не рассказывай мне Польшу Смотри
there is a Crimea, there is a Kursk region
вот есть Крым есть Курская область
Why do you have the Kursk region?
Почему у тебя Курская область это
is occupied by Ukraine and Crimea is
оккупирована Украиной а Крым - это
Russia
Россия
because they held a referendum there, they
потому что туда провели референдум
installed power, consolidated it all from a
поставили власть закрепили это всё с
point in the Kursk region, yes they installed
точки в Курской области да поставили
power, yes they did, military administrations
власть Да сделали военные администрации
conducted everything from the point of view of Ukraine, yes,
вели всё с точки зрения Украины Да
that’s all. Well, I’m talking at the moment Ukraine
всё Ну я говорю на данный момент Украина
Russia is now paying pensions in the
Россия сейчас выплачивает пенсии в
city  Sudzha Russia is now repairing
городе Суджа Россия сейчас ремонтирует
roads there Russia is now bringing
там дороги Россия сейчас там носит
food to people there No, well, I’m saying In
продукты людям Нет ну вот я говорю В
this regard, that is, right there and then it’s
этом плане то есть тут же тут же это
Ukraine Yes, well, at the moment it’s
Украина Да вот ну на данный момент это
objective Well, objectively That is, right there
же объективно Ну объективно То есть тут
it’s Ukraine and Russia doesn’t have the
же это Украина да Россия не имеет
opportunity  manage this all that
возможности управлять этой те всё то
is right there it’s Ukraine Yes well at the
есть тут же это Украина Да ну на данный
moment yes yes all the same Ukraine okay Ukraine is not
момент да да всё сут же Украина окей Не
occupied just a court it’s
оккупирована Украина просто суд же это
Ukraine so that we understand
Украина чтобы мы поняли
so it’s considered
так счита
just no well I just wanted to Why
просто нет ну я хотел просто Почему про
say about Poland it’s just an example that
Польшу сказать это просто пример который
can’t  does not apply to those simply As an
никак не относится ни к тем просто Как
example of military operations, that is, there
пример боевых действий то есть
is a German army there, the Soviet army
есть там немецкая армия Советской армия
enters the territory of Poland, they occupy it,
заходят на территорию Польши они её
until a certain moment it is located as an
до определённого момента находится как
occupation territory, then they
оккупационной территория потом там
make a re-commissariat there and that’s when they make
делают ре комиссариат и вот когда делают
Remit
Ремит
territory And one way or another
территория А так или иначе
annexed
присоединённая
and then  yes, you want to say, that is, you
и То есть ты хочешь сказать то есть ты
want to say that the territories in which there
хочешь сказать что территории на которых
were territories of the Soviet Union
был территории Советского Союза
Yes, in which there was a Reich Reich Commissariat
Да на которых был Рей Рейх комиссариат
Yes, they were no longer territories of the
Да они уже не были территориями
Soviet Union
Советского Союза
Yes, well, from the point of view of Poland until the
Да ну с точки зрения Польши до того
moment when the Poles resisted
момента пока поляки сопротивлялись
until the Polish army capitulated then
пока польская армия не капитулировала то
yes
да
yes What does the Polish army have to do with this, we are talking
да Причём тут польская армия мы говорим
about the commissariat flight, for example, Crimea
про рейс комиссариат вот Крым например
was under German occupation, all this is
да был под немецкой оккупацией всё это
no longer the case, the Soviet Union
уже получается не Советский Союз
was then when the
был тогда получается когда тогда
Soviet Union did not liberate these
Советский Союз не освободил эти
territories, it occupied it, so it turns out
территории оккупировал так получается
that this was already a republican commissariat,
что это был уже рес комиссариат
this was already the third  rei here the Soviet
это уже был третий реи тут Советский
Union occupied so it turns out
Союз оккупировал так получается
By the way, I remembered the example about this
Не кстати вспомнил пример про это
Lokot formation on the
локотское образование на
territory this was definitely not the
территории вот это вот это был точно не
Soviet Union, a completely different
Советский Союз уже совершенно другое
formation under the Germans under the
образование под под немцами под
occupation not according to That is, it turns out that the
оккупационный не по То есть получается
Soviet Union occupied the tray of
Советский соз оккупировал лотку
the Republic of the Republic Yes, but from the point  from the
республику Республики Да но с точки
point of view of the Soviet Union, he was returning
зрения Советского Союза он возвращал
his territories that he had lost,
свои территории которые он потерял свои
not everything he doesn’t control, he doesn’t
не всё он не контролирует он там не
pay a pension there, he’s not there, that’s not
платит пенсию он там не это то это не
his, yes, well, he’s returning what that is. What does it
его да Ну он возвращает то что Что
mean returning what was everything, it’s not
значит возвращает то что было всё оно не
yours, returning what once-  then it was
твоё возвращает то что когда-то было
yours, it’s an occupation, then it
твоё это оккупация тогда
turns out, well, from the point of view of the gloss of
получается ну с точки зрения лоско
education, the gloss of the Republic is an
образования лоско Республики это
occupation, it’s really an occupation, they do
оккупация это действительно оккупация у
n’t already have needs there, well, everything is like that
не же там уже нужди с то Ну так всё так
from the point of view of the Soviet Union, it’s also an
с точки зрения Советского Союза это тоже
occupation, they have their own mayors, if that’s how
оккупация там свои мэры если вот как как
look like Lokotskaya  republic Yes, they have
смотри как локотская республика Да там
their own mayors, and in Crimea now they really elected their own mayors, they
свои мэры так и в Крыму сейчас свои мэры
installed Aksyonova Well, everything is
правда выбрали поставили аксёново Ну всё
like the Lokot
как локотская
Republic Well, in the situation of, say, the beginning of the
республика Ну в ситуации скажем начала
Second World War and the Great
Второй Мировой войны а Великой
Patriotic War, as it were, forty-
Отечественной войны как бы сорок первого
one, this war continues, it does not
года это война продолжается она не
end And while it continues
заканчивается И пока она продолжается
Not yet  truce peace negotiations,
Пока нет перемирия мирного переговора
uh, the Soviet Union returns or does not
она ээ Советский Союз возвращает или не
return super, so look, did Ukraine
возвращает супер так смотри а у Украины
have a Peace Treaty with Russia on
был Мирный мирный договор с Россией по
Crimea or not? Well, there was no war then,
Крыму или нет Ну и войны же тогда не
since the
было никакой так как с четырнадцатого
War has been going on since 1914. Well, they didn’t
года идёт Война да Ну там же не
declare any war there  and even now they have
объявляли войну никакую так и и сейчас
n’t declared now, didn’t someone declare
не объявили сейчас разве кто-то объявил
war, no
войну
one declared theirs and war and there is no need to
никто не объявлял сво а войну и не надо
declare there is no such thing that it is necessary to declare
Объявлять нет такого что нужно объявить
war, you know, I’m not educated in politics,
войну Вы знаете я в политике не
after all, it’s even worse than in
образован всё-таки ещё хуже чем в
cultural studies,
культурологии
I want to respectfully
хочется уважительно
and meaningfully with  giving back with some kind of
и со смыслом с отдачей с какой-то что
respect for
уважительно
the topic, after all, it’s not me
тему всё-таки Не меня
we’re discussing, it’s not me, it’s
обсуждаем вопросы мы обсуждаем не меня
not you, we’re discussing your attitude towards
не вас мы обсуждаем ваше отношение на
aggressiveness on
захватнические
this issue. Why should a slave have an opinion, do you
этому поводу Зачем рабу иметь мнение ты
mean that, or
так имеешь в виду или
what, by the way, was very important for
что кстати очень актуально было для
Greece in ancient times  but for you
Греции в своё время антично а для тебя
it’s relevant I just don’t consider myself a
актуально Я просто не считаю себя
slave but you’re not interested in politics Yes you
рабом но не интересуешься политиком Да
don’t influence anything And so on And that’s all And
ничего не влияешь И так дальше И всё И
in short Why do you need to have an opinion Yes
короче Зачем тебе иметь мнение Да
No, of course I have an opinion But I
Нет у меня конечно есть мнение Но вам
won’t
его не
tell you it You’re
скажу ты
afraid I just think
боишься Я просто считаю
that it’s like-  it has to be intimate
что это как-то должно интимно
somehow, not in the
как-то не на
situation, it’s intimate, that is, it’s scary to
ситуации оно интимно то есть его страшно
say, but suddenly a comrade major will hear and
сказать да вдруг услышит товариш майор и
put you in jail. And this is not slavery, you want to
посадит И это не рабство ты хочешь
say, No, well, I’m going there, I’ll tell you, I’ll
сказать Нет ну я же туда отно я скажу я
tell you why I, I left Russia 18 years ago,
скажу почему я я 18 лет как выехал из
yes  and I live in California I
России да и живу в Калифорнии Я
felt what freedom is, here in
почувствовал что такое свобода я тут в
California I can say anything about Trump or
Калифорнии могу говорить на трампа на
Biden, I’m not afraid to have my own
байдена что угодно я не боюсь иметь своё
opinion. Why am I a free person and my
мнение Почему я свободный человек а мой
father is in Russia in Rostov and
отец в России в Ростове а
he doesn’t want to voice his position at work
он не хочет озвучить на работе свою
because he’s
позицию потому
afraid  why Well, this is an objective
боится почему Ну этоже объективный
circumstance. This is slavery,
обстоятельство Вот это и есть рабство
this is slavery. Yes, he is afraid. Because he
это рабство Да он боится Потому что его
will be fired from his
уволят с
job there. And so on, all this
работы там да И так дальше всё это
slavery, you don’t have your own opinion;  to
рабство ты не имеешь свого мнения
say This is
Калифорнии и ты боишься сказать Вот это
simple, if I lived in Russia, I might
просто если бы я жил в России я бы может
not have felt this after 18 years of living in
это не ощущал после 18 лет жизни в
California, for me it’s crazy that a person is
Калифорнии для меня это дико что человек
afraid to say his opinion politically,
боится сказать своё мнение политическо
this is just for us in America, if you
это просто для нас в Америке ты если бы
said something like that, they would look at you
такое сказать на тебя посмотрели
like Kato Well, as you
какой-то типа Като Ну как это ты
understand,
понимаешь
they are really scary,
те реально страшно
I agree about this, as
я по этому поводу я согласен здесь как
if
бы
I agree, that is, different political
я я согласен то есть разные политические
systems, different
устройства разные
countries. The United States is very
страны Соединённые Штаты же очень сильно
different from European countries in
отличаются от европейских стран во
many ways, the history of development is of course a
многом истории развития конечно
unique country, that it is an absolutely
уникальная страна что это абсолютно
unique
уникальная
country.  If I'm not mistaken Freedom to name She,
страна Если не ошибаюсь Свобода наме Она
come on T in the end you may have an
же давай Т напоследок у тебя может КАТО
interesting question for
интересный вопрос ко
me, can I think about it Now a minute
мне можно я подумаю Сейчас минуту
Good question, maybe it was your question
Хороший вопрос можно это был твой вопрос
that you used I said one
который ты использовал Я сказал один
question you can ask You asked, can I, I'll
вопрос можешь задать Ты спросил можно я
think about it, you can Come on,
подумаю можно Давай
think about it, even your own  question at the
думай он даже свой вопрос в
end like squeak comment so that we are not
конце лайк писка комент чтобы мы не был
slaves Yak oti Russians Glory to Ukraine
рабами Як оти россияне Слава Украине
write on th Instagram I don’t know for this,
пись на й Instagram Я не знаю для це то
for that, there to marvel at oe and for you, odi
для то там дивитись на ое а для тебе оди
atri clique and you trime me and I will ka
атри клика а ты тримае мене и я буду ка
me there Kupa fouls  in me there will be a cool
мене там Купа фолов в мене буде класний
mood, robiti but cool video message on th
настр щоб робити но крут вдео пись на й
Instagram pova
Instagram пова